اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
We'll move on to the next section and that is the Ghazawat(غزوأت), the Fatoohaat(فتوحات ).
The conquests that occurred in the time of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه .
In our books of history, these would be called a Ghazawat(غزوأت).
What does the word Ghazwa(غزوة) mean.?
Now, the word has a specific meaning in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then it has a more general meaning after that.
In the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ, battles would be called either Ghazwa(غزوة) or Sariyyah(سرية).
Now, originally the word Ghazoo(غزؤ) linguistically means to raid, to attack,
that's the meaning of Ghazoo(غزؤ).
However, in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ this word was used to specifically mean
a battle in which Rasool Allah ﷺ led.
A battle in Which Rasool Allah ﷺ did not lead is called Sariyyah(سرية).
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ would send the Sahabah(صحابه) it would be called Sariyyah(سرية).
When he would lead the army himself, it would be called Ghazwa(غزوة).
With one exception and that is Ghazwat Maota(غزوة موته).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not involved in Maota(موته),
he appointed Zaid Ibn Harisa(زيدبن حارثه) to be the leader and if he is killed then Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفرإبن أبي طالب)
and if he is killed Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة).
But it was called Ghazwa(غزوة) because of the great importance of that battle.
Since, this was a confrontation between the Muslims and the Romans.
It was a large army of about 3000.
So, it was given the classification of a Ghazwa(غزوة).
Later on, after Rasool Allah ﷺ,
in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), and after that any battle whatsoever would be called a Ghazwa(غزوة).
So, we're now talking about the Ghazawat(غزوات) that occurred in the time of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
In the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) the fronts that were opened in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) carried on.
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه opened up two new fronts,
the Persian front and the Roman front
and it's quite interesting to see that Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه who ruled for a little over two years
did all of that within this short span.
He is the one, who led the wars against Al-Murtadden(ألمرتدين), the apostates.
He is the one, who finished it, and then immediately he opened up consciously, by choice,
he is the one, who provoked both the Persian and the Roman Empires simultaneously.
The Roman Empire was in Ash-Sham(ألشام), the Persian Empire was in Al-Iraq.
Abubakar Siddique رضي الله عنه decides that he's going to attack both of them,
and he will do it in the same time.
He started with Al-Iraq which was part of the Persian Empire, and then he moved in to As-Sham(ألشام).
However, these battles were not completed, in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), death took him away.
So Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه carried on,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) finished with the opening of Iraq and Ash-Sham(ألشام).
He's the one who opened Jerusalem and then he carried on to further lands.
So, he crossed over to Africa and opened Egypt and parts of Libya.
And also Iran was opened during the era of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه .
So, we'll start with the Iraqi front.
And this was very concerning to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
and in his Wasiah(وصية), before he died,
he gave him Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) specific instructions
on carrying on the Jihad Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله ) in the land of Iraq.
The Persians had a reputation of being tough fighters, they're very strong.
So, Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه was mobilizing the Muslims of Madina
and all over the Muslim world to volunteer for this Ghazoo(غزؤ),
because at that time Ghazoo(غزؤ) was a voluntary
and there wasn't any mandatory recruiting.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه is calling upon the Muslims to join the ranks of the army
the first day, nobody shows up
and we're talking about, and we say nobody showed up, we're talking about leaders,
because in those days, people were clans, they were tribes.
So, and these people would usually move together, the bonding was very strong family ties.
So, an entire tribe would come forth,
you know, he didn't really have a lot of individuals coming on their own,
the tribal leader would make a decision, all of his people would follow him.
You'd have obviously some individuals here and there, stepping in
but in general, it was tribes moving along in cohesion.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is calling for these leaders to come forth
the first day nobody showed up,
second day no one shows up, the third day nobody shows up.
Finally Abu Obaid As-Saqafi(أبوعبيدألثَّقفي) who's from At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف)
and he's not a companion he steps forth and he volunteers.
After him one of Al-Ansaar, Sulait Bin Qais(سليت بن قيس) he comes forth and he also volunteers
and then some of the other Ansaar(أنْصَار) joined in.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) appointed Abu Obaid As-Saqafi(أبوعبيدألثَّقفي) to lead the army that would go to Iraq.
The Sahabah(صحابه) were in the army, they said:
why don't you appoint one of the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) or Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار)?
Why don't you appoint one of these Sahabah(صحابه) to lead this army?
How come you're appointing a Tabiee(تابعي)?.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه said;
إِنَّمَا أُأَمِّرِوْ أَوَّلَ مَنِ السَّتَجَابَ
إِنَّكُمْ إِنَّمَا سَبَقْتُمْ النَّاسَ بِنُصْرَتِ هَذَالدِّيْنَ
He said: I'm going to appoint the one who came first,
you are ahead of everyone else because you became Muslim first,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is telling the Sahabah(صحابه).
The reason why you have a special status is because you became Muslim before everyone else.
Because this man, he came first to lead this army, I will appoint him to lead the army.
Since, he is the first one to volunteer.
And therefore you can see the importance of As-Saabiqa(أسّابقه).
As-Saabiqa(أسّابقه) is hastening towards good.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
إِنَّهُمْ كَانُوا يُسَارِعُونَ فِي الْخَيْرَاتِ وَيَدْعُونَنَا رَغَبًا وَرَهَبًا ۖ
They used to hasten towards good.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
وَالسَّابِقُونَ السَّابِقُونَ أُولَئِكَ الْمُقَرَّبُونَ۝
The forerunners, the forerunners, they are the ones, who will be close to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So, the time of your commitment to the truth is important.
Therefore, those who are planning to take advantage of their young years,
and commit everything sin under the sun and then after that we're going to go on Hajj(حَجْ)
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will forgive everything.
We will grow a beard and go in the Masjid(مسجد), retire in the Masjid(مسجد) and that's it.
It doesn't work that way.
Yes, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ excepts the toba(توبة) as long as it is before the Sakaraat-Ul-Maot(سكراةالموت)
before the soul is coming out of the body.
But, obviously the status of such a person is way different
than somebody, who grew into Islam and who practice Islam day in and day out.
Rasool Allah ﷺ talks about the seven, who would be provided with shade
under the throne of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on the Day of Judgment.
One of them is,
شَابُ نَّشَاءْ فِيْ طَاعَتِ الله
A young man, who was practicing Islam from a young age.
Such a person will be provided with shade under the throne of Allah
on a day that is 50,000 years long.
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه is the first to enter into Jannah(جنة),
after the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) on the Day of Judgment.
Because he was the first to respond to the call of Muhammad ﷺ
he is the Sabiq(سابق).
Now, with Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), the amazing thing
is that not only was he first in becoming Muslim, he was ahead in everything.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) who came in later on, would  try to compete with Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
try to get the gold medal at least in one thing,
and they never succeeded in doing so.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
وَاللهِ لَا أُسَابِقُوْ أَبِيْ بَكَرْ أَبَدًا
In the name of Allah, I'm never going to try to compete with him, again.
Ali Bin Abi Talib رضي الله عنه says;
وَكَانَ سَبَّاقًا فِيْ كُلِّ خَيْرَ
He was ahead of us in everything that is good,
he was the first in everything, first place.
And we talked about the Sahabi(صحابي) who saw Rasool Allah ﷺ and Khadijah(خديجه) and Ali Bin Abi Talib praying
and he never really took that seriously and then years later, he became Muslim.
And he said, If I became Muslim on that day, and he regretted the fact that he didn't become Muslim early on,
and they only became Muslim after the Fath(فتح) of At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
And that holds true today, the earlier you start practicing, the better off you are,
the earlier you try to study Ilm(علم), the better off you are,
the earlier you start to incorporate Qiyaam-Ul-Lail(قيام الّيل) into your life,
the better off you are.
And when you do such things in young age,
when you're still like a soft branch on a tree.
When that branch becomes hard, the wood becomes hard.
All of those things that you were doing becomes second natured to you,
and you carry on doing them for the rest of your life.
But when the branches already stiff, it's very difficult to move it.
So, trying to change yourself when you're old is not as easy as when you're young.
Somebody who tries to memorize Qur'an when they're old would find it much more difficult
than if they do it when they're young.
Somebody who tries to study Islam when they are old would find it very difficult.
I'm not saying that you shouldn't do it, you should carry on
because you are rewarded for the effort you put into it.
But the thing is, anything that you do the earlier you do it, the better off you are.
And this gives you Barakah(بركة) for the rest of your life.
You know, don't be like the brothers of Yousaf(يوسف) who plotted against him.
See, the brothers of Yousaf, they said: we're gonna kill Yousaf(يوسف) and then make Toba(توبة)
that was their plan.
Let's kill him and make Toba(توبة) later on.
Well, they did make Toba(توبة) eventually,
but look at the difference in status between them and Yousaf(يوسف),
they were never ever able to catch up.
So, you miss out on a lot of things when you join in late
and that is the case also in joining any
أَمْرابِالّْمَعْرُوْفَ وَنَهِيْ اَلْمُنْكَرْ
It is also true with any revivalist movement or revivalist call.
The people who join in early are the ones who leave away with the most Ajr(أجْر).
Take for example, and this is something from the future
but we can use it as an example
with Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي) how many people will give Bay'ah(بيعه) to Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي) initially,
a little over 300.
Out of all of the Ummah(امة) and only Allah knows
what the population of the Muslim Ummah(امة) will be then.
And now, we are a billion and a quarter.
Out of the entire Muslim Ummah(امة) only little over 300 will give him Bay'ah(بيعه)
and these are the ones, whom Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will grant the highest Ajr(أجْر).
Later on, a miracle will happen with Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي)
because an army will try to attack him from Iraq.
And Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي) and his followers are in Makkah.
This army when it's on its way to attack and Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي), the Earth would swallow it.
The Earth would just swallow up the entire army because this is a supernatural event.
It's a miracle and it is mentioned in the Ahadith(احاديث),
then everyone will know that this man is the Mahdi(ألمهدي).
And everyone will go and give him Bay'ah(بيعة).
But if it's done then, we're not saying that it's too late.
But it's too late to get the great Ajr(أجْر),
then it's a public thing everybody knows about it, everybody is doing it.
So, it's the early 300, who would leave away with the highest levels in the eyes of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
also with Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
لَا يَنْفَعُوْ نَفْسٌ إِيْمَانُهَا لَمْ تَكًنْ أَمَنَتْ مِنْ قَبْلَ أَوْ كَسَبَتْ فِيْ إِيْمَانِهَا خَيْرًا
Rasool Allah ﷺ says when Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال) comes out publicly with his invitation to falsehood
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
A person who doesn't already have Emaan(إيمان) will not be able to attain it then.
If you're not prepared in advance you will not be able to prepare when he comes out.
So, you have to have prior preparation to be saved from the Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال)
because his Fitnah(فِتْنَه) is so great no one will be able to attain Emaan(إيمان) when he comes out.
So, you can see the value of being ahead,
being ahead in everything
and I'm saying this because of our tendency to have procrastination, we delay things.
Ibn Qayyim(إبن قيم) in fact he says;
If one would go through the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an which narrate
what the people of Hellfire are saying
one would find that the majority of their complaints are?
How come we delayed it?
Why did we wait?
Why did we procrastinate?
رَبّ ارْجِعُونِ لَعَلِّي أَعْمَلُ صَالِحًا فِيمَا تَرَكْتُ ۚ
O Allah Take me back, so that I can do good.
In another Ayah(آية) it says: O Allah take me back to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), so that I can make Infaaq(إنفاق) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
In another Ayah(آية) it says: O Allah take me back to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
I will believe in you and in the messenger and on and on.
They delayed it, until it was too late.
Abu Obaidah As-Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) he came first,
he was appointed even though he had less experience in war.
He was a Tabaee(تابعي) and not a Sahabi(صحابي).
So in terms of status is lower than the Sahabah(صحابه), the Sahabah(صحابه) are higher
But because he came first, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) appointed him.
Sulait(سُلَيت) who is from Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I would have appointed him
but this Ansari(أنصاري) was in a rush.
He wasn't a person who takes issues calmly, he rushes into things.
He is very bold and aggressive and strong.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn't mind the person having such characteristics
but he did not want such a person to lead an army.
So, Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه told Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي), he said:
إِسْمِعْ لِأَصْحَابِ رَسُوْلِ الله وَشِّرِكْهُمْ فِى الّأَمْر
Listen to the advice of the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and
take Shura(شورى) from them, take their advice.
وَلَا تَجْتَعِدْ مُسْرِعًا
بَلِتَّعِدْفَإِنَّهَا الّحَرْبَ لَا يُصْلِحُوْهَا إِلَّا رَجُلٌ مَقِيْسَ أَلَّذِيْ يَعْرِفُ الّفُرْسَا
And do not be in a hurry and take it easy and slow down because this is war
and only a man whose unrushed is appropriate to lead in a battle.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is saying that when it comes to war,
the person who is leading the army needs to be a person who is unrushed, not in a hurry,
who deliberates and looks at things from every and each angle and doesn't rush into affairs.
Why?
Because the lives of the Muslims are under your hands.
And he said;
وَلَا يَمْنَعَنِيْ أَنْ أَأُمِّرْ صُلَيْتًّا إِلَّا سّْرَتَه’ الّحَرْبَ
The only reason why I'm not pointing Sulait(سُلَيت) is because he rushes things
and Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
"أَلْأَجَلَ مِنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ"
Hastening things is from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)
because when you do things in a rush, you're prone to make mistakes.
And Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) uses these mistakes against you.
Now, this doesn't mean that you should be so slow that you don't get anything done.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he says;
"وَيَتَحَيَّرُالّفُرْسَا"
A man who's unrushed but takes advantage of opportunities.
So, when you see an opportunity you take it you go for it, you don't wait
and think about it and no you go and take advantage of it.
Abu Obaidah Assaqafi رضي الله عنه leads this army of about 7000
in the end he was able to mobilize the force of 10,000 before he met with the enemy
and he travelled towards Al-Iraq.
They reached to a river and the enemy is across the river, the other side
and now they're prepared to fight.
So the enemy's General, he told Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي),
Are you going to cross to us?
Or shall we cross over to you?
The Muslims told Abu Obaid(أبوعبيد); Let them cross over to us.
Abu Obaid(أبوعبيد) Said: No.
إِنَّهُمْ لَيْسُ بِأَجْرَأَلّْمَوْتِ مِنَّا
They are not more willing to die than we are.
So, let's cross over to them.
So, they crossed over this bridge and they reached to the other side of the river.
But the problem is that they were in a very narrow area,
the enemy did not give them sufficient room to move in.
So, they were constrained, they were constricted and the battle started
and the Persians employed a weapon, which was unfamiliar to the Arabs
and that was the elephant.
They used elephants to fight and these were well trained elephants.
And you would have soldiers on top of these elephants
and they attached to the elephants bells
that would make a very raging, ringing sound very loud
and that spooked the horses.
So, now the entire Muslim cavalry was neutralized,
none of the horses was willing to attack because of this violent sound
that they would hear coming from the elephants.
So, you have the entire cavalry is now out of the battle.
So, now only the Muslim infantry was involved,
and the archers were hitting them from every direction.
So, the Muslims were dropping.
Abu Obaidah Assaqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) realize the difficulty of the situation.
He said: We have to get rid of these elephants, otherwise, we'll be massacred
our horses are not able to attack and we are on foot and we are facing the elephants.
We are facing their cavalry and we are facing their foot soldiers.
And the Muslim cavalry was the most important portion of the army.
That's where the Fursaan(فرسان) are, the fighters are.
So, Abu Obaidah Assaqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) gave his commands;
Go and cut the ropes that are holding the saddles,
because every elephant has a saddle on top of it,
and there are group of soldiers on top of the elephant.
So, Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) thought, if we're able to bring down those soldiers from on top of the elephants,
then the elephants would be without anyone to lead them.
So, they went around cutting the saddles, until they drop them from on top of the elephants.
But that did not solve the problem because these were trained elephants,
and they were just stumbling across the army,
stepping over Muslims and crushing them under their feet.
Abu Obaidah Assaqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) said: We must then kill these elephants.
But these are huge animals.
How can you kill the elephant with the sword or a spear or an arrow?
Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) asked: How can we get rid of them?
They said: Cut the trunk, if you cut the trunk of the elephant, it would die.
That's what they, that's the advice he was given.
Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) himself, even though he's the leader of the army,
he went ahead in order to cut off the trunk of this elephant.
But when he attempted to reach to the trunk of the elephant,
the elephant struck Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيد) with his foot and stepped over Abu Obaid(ابوعبيد) and crushed him,
Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي), the Ameer(أمير) of the Muslim army died, Shaheed(شهيد).
His brother took over and he went to attack the same elephant, and was again crushed.
So, his brother, Al-Hakam Bin Masood(ألحكم بن مسعود) died.
They carried on.
Now, Abu Obaid(ابوعبيد) appointed seven of his family members as Umaraa(أمرآء) in case he dies.
So, if he died, it's his brother and his brother died, then it's his son,
if his son dies, then his other son anyway, seven of his family members to assume leadership in case he dies.
All of the seven were killed, all of the seven from the same family of Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) were killed.
At the end of the day Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Shaibaani(ألْمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني),
he assumed the Imara(عمارة) of the army and he asked the Muslims to retreat.
Al-Musanna(ألمثنى) saw that in this situation, we have a justified reason for retreating
we should not carry on fighting, so he asked the Muslims to retreat.
So, the Muslims are going on this bridge,
Abdullah bin Marsad As-Saqqafi(عبدالله بن مرصد الثقفي) he went to the bridge and he told the Muslims;
We should die just like our leaders died, do not retreat.
Maybe this was before Musanna(مثنى) gave his instructions but anyway,
the Muslims were already retreating even before the instructions of Al-Musanna(ألمثنى).
So, the Muslims were retreating and Abdullah Bin Marsad(عبدالله بن مرصد) went to the bridge
and he was telling the Muslims do not retreat, we should fight and die like our leaders did.
And what did he do?
He cut the bridge.
You know this was a rope bridge, so he cut it down
he was brought to Al-Musanna(ألمثنى).
Al-Musanna(ألمثنى) beaten him so badly and, he said;
Why did you do that?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said: I did so that they would carry on fighting.
Al-Musanna Bin Harisa(ألمثنى بن حارثه) gave his instructions that the bridge should be tied again.
And that the Muslims should retreat, he saw it as a fatal thing to do.
We have no chance of winning this battle, we need to retreat
the elephants were just massacring the Muslims.
The cavalry was not involved in the fighting,
he asked the Muslims to retreat and Al-Musanna(ألمثنى) told them;
"I want you to retreat peacefully and I am going to protect you
until you all reach to the other side and then I will cross over."
So, Al-Musanna Bin Harisa(ألمثنى بن حارثه), he is the leader but he wants to ensure that he leaves the last.
By the way, Abdullah Bin Marsad(عبدالله بن مرصد) when it cut down the bridge, what happened is
there are many Muslims already on their way to crossing the bridge.
So, they were very close to the river
and because the army of the enemy was so close to them and was pushing them many of them fell in the river and died,
they drowned in the river.
4000 Muslims were killed in that battle
it's called the Battle of the bridge, 4000 many of them were Sahabah(صحابه).
Now, when you say 4000, in those days that's a very high number.
6000 Persians were killed.
Musanna Bin Harisa(ألمثنى بن حارثه) retreated with the army and he went back to Madina.
FEW THINGS RELATING TO THIS BATTLE, THE BATTLE OF AL-JISR(ألجسر)
Number one; The wife of Abu Obaidah As-Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي), her name is Daoma(دومه)
she saw a dream.
She saw someone come from the heavens with a vessel in his hand
and her husband Abu Obaid(ابوعبيد) came to drink from that vessel
and then his son came to drink and his brother came to drink
and she mentioned, the names of seven of his relatives.
Abu Obaid As-Saqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) said: This indicates Shahadah(شهادة)
the interpretation of this dream is Shahadah(شهادة).
And that's why, he appointed these seven men to lead the army after him.
Because he felt that these would die as Shuhada(شهداء).
So, when he appointed them as leaders it's not as an honoring or a special status
it is to put them in the front line, in the line of fire.
To put them in the most risky post
and his interpretation was true all of them died as a Shaheed(شهيد).
When it comes to dreams brothers and sisters dreams are not interpreted equally
so for example here, this means Shahadah(شهادة) that's not the only way
Shahadah(شهادة) presents itself in a dream.
With Tufail Bin Amr(طفيل بن عمرو) for example he saw that birds were eating from his head
and that he was swallowed into a womb of a woman.
He said: The interpretation of this dream is that my head will be chopped off
and I will die as a Shaheed(شهيد)
and the womb swallowing him is the earth swallowing his body, in his grave.
So, that was Shahadah(شهادة).
The way some people see Shahadah(شهادة) is
they see themselves talking to Al-Hoor Ul Ain(حورالعين) before they die.
With some, for example with Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان),
Rasool Allah ﷺ came to him and his dream and he said;
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) was fasting that day.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came to him in his dream and said: You're going to have Aftar(أفطار) with me
and he died that day.
So, Shahadah(شهادة) can come in different forms.
So, the interpretation of dreams is more of  a gift from Allah than it is a science.
We can also see that dreams played an important role in their lives.
I mean, they would see dreams, they would interpret the dreams
because this is the only thing remaining from Prophet hood.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: That all of the Prophethood will end with him
and the only thing that will remain is,
أَلرُّوْيَهْ أَلصَّادِقَهْ يَرَاهَلْ عَبْدَ الْمُؤمِنَ
Is the true dream that a believer would see.
So, this is the only form of revelation or inspiration that remains.
Jibril عليه السّلام will never come down and deliver revelation to anyone.
So, the only way in which we receive some of the ilm(علم) of the unseen is through dreams
that are seen by Al-Momineen(ألمؤمنين) and these are Bisharat(بشارات).
I think we talked earlier that there is no Halal(حلال) and Haram(حرام) that comes through a dream.
The dream is only a Bishara(بشارة) it's good news, it's an indication of what will happen
you cannot take a dream and use it to drive Ahkam(أحكام).
The Ahkam(أحكام) are in Qur'an, and Sunnah(سنة).
Number two, there were two mistakes committed,
Number one: Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) not listening to the advice of his generals.
When they said: Do not cross over to them, let them cross over to us.
Abu Obaidah Saqqafi(أبوعبيد ألثقفي) was eager to go and fight,
he saw it as an inappropriate for them to come to us
because we want to die more than them
and the Persians surrounded them because of that.
Number two: The second mistake was Abdullah Bin Marsad(عبدالله بن مرصد), cutting the bridge
and that was putting the Muslims in a very difficult situation.
They're unable to retreat and it was too difficult for them to fight
because the ranks were not organized and because of the elephants.
So, bravery is good it's encouraged virtue, however, too much of that turns into recklessness.
In fact, sometimes a person could be reckless even if they're a coward.
A Muslim is supposed to have courage but they're not supposed to be reckless.
A Muslim is supposed to think out things approach affairs with wisdom
and not rush into anything because again, being in a hurry is from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
ألعجل من الشّيطان
Number three;
"وَمَنْ يَتَّقِلَ الله يَجْعَلْ لَه’ مَخْرَجَا "
The ones who have Taqwa(تقوى) in Allah, Allah will provide a way out for them.
The Muslims were in a very, very difficult situation.
Yes they retreated but they were still in the land of the enemy
and the enemy could take advantage of that and just wipe them out, massacre them all,
because 4000 Muslims were killed you only had a few thousand left
and the enemy was 10s of thousands, they could recruit more.
But Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, when He wants to save His followers
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ creates the circumstances that facilitate saving them.
You see Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is the One, Who controls everything in the heavens and earth.
You might look at it in the beginning and say if you're looking at it
from an approach of one plus one equals two logically.
It's impossible the Muslims will be wiped out.
But keep in mind that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has promised that
He would give assistance and help to Muttaqeen(ألمتقين).
Yes, the Muslims have lost in this battle.
They couldn't find the cure for the elephants issue
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ created for them a climate that made it impossible on the Persians
to look at the Islamic invasion of their land,
and that is a dispute that broke out between Rustum(رستم) and Feroze(فيروز).
Rustum(رستم) and Feroze(فيروز), were the highest two military leaders in Persia.
A war or a fight, a dispute broke out between the two of them
and that preoccupied them from looking into the Muslim army.
So, even though the Muslim army was weak and was battered in that war,
many of them are injured, they lost some of their best fighters but nobody attack them.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ saved them through this dispute.
Just like a Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has prepared the grounds for the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Right before Muhammad ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina,
one of the worst battles between Al-Aus(ألأوس) and Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج) occurred
and it was called the Youm-Ul-Buaas(أليوم بعاث).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said: Yaoum Buaas(أليوم بعاث) was a day of preparation for the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
because that is when the majority of the leaders of both camps were killed.
So, the people were left without leaders
and that enhanced their willingness to bring in a leader from outside - Muhammad ﷺ.
If the people of Madina were living in a peaceful state,
they wouldn't have wanted to bring in somebody from outside to lead them.
Why would anyone want to bring a leader, a foreign leader from outside
and appoint him over them if everything is going on alright?
But because they have been in this cycle of violence for a very long time
Al-Aus(ألأوس) Wal-Khazraj(وألخزرج) at each other's necks for years and years
because of the Battle of Buaas(بعاث) many of the leaders were killed.
When they went to Muhammad ﷺ they said: Maybe Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will unify us
and end the bloodshed that is happening among us, through you.
So, that war of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) that was going on between Al-Aus(ألأوس) Wal-Khazraj(وألخزرج)
was a preparation for the Hijrah(هجرة) of Muhammad ﷺ.
It was also another preparation
because it made the men of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) the most ideal group to given nusra(نصرة) to Muhammad ﷺ.
They were seasoned fighters, what they would do?
Is wake up in the morning go and fight until night time and they would go back to bed, on a daily basis.
The training was part of their life the fighting was part of their life.
It was a prepared and ready army for Rasool Allah ﷺ, to take over.
It was an honor that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has preserved for them,
even though it happened through hardship.
They suffered for years and years
but that was a preparation for them to be the Ansaar(ألأنصار) of this religion.
The ones who would give this religion a victory.
Therefore, the Muslim should never give up, the Muslim should never fear the creation
and say that the creation is stronger than me, is more better equipment than me,
has more technology than me, I have no hope that's not how you should look at it,
the way you should look at it is.
If I have Taqwa(تقوى) Allah will give me victory
no matter how strong the enemy is.!
If I  don't have Taqwa(تقوى) Allah will humiliate me, no matter how weak my enemy is.
It all goes back to Taqwa(تقوى).
And in the future when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will see that this Ummah(امة) deserves victory,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will prepare the circumstances that will facilitate that,
No matter how wide the gap in technology is, no matter how wide the financial gap is,
all of these issues are irrelevant,
when it comes to the issue of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ giving victory to the ones who He loves.
There is no way to compare between the strength of Musa عليه السّلام and Firaun(فرعون), no way.
What are you going to compare Musa alone, عليه السّلام, against Firaun(فرعون).
أَلَّذِيْ تَجْرِى لّْأَنْهَارُ مِنْ تَحْتِهَا
Firaun(فرعون) says; Rivers are flowing under me.
He was the superpower of the Earth at that time, he had the most powerful army in the world,
he had all of the wealth you could ask for, he had the powerful security force, he had it all,
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ made him commit mistakes that ended with his demise.
Even though Firaun(فرعون) was intelligent leader, he was a wise man, with very strong abilities.
He had the powerful army, he had the resources,
he had the advisors to tell him how to plan and how to approach the problem of Musa(موسى) and Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل).
And on the other hand, you had Musa(موسى) and Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل) are
without any arms without any wealth, they were slaves, they were weak.
But Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ made firaoun(فرعون), commit mistakes and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ guided Musa(موسى).
Musa عليه السّلام said;
كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّ مَعِيَ رَبِّي سَيَهْدِينِ
When Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل) said: O Musa(موسى) give up that's it, they're gonna kill us
we have no chance, sea is in front of us and Firaun(فرعون) is behind us. What  can we do?
We are without any weapons you promised us and you lied.
You said, that Allah is going to save us and here we are,
the sea in front of us, Firaun(فرعون) behind us, you tricked us, you fooled us.
And they were going on, and on, and on and on… What did Musa(موسى) say?
كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّ مَعِيَ رَبِّي سَيَهْدِينِ
No! Allah is with me and He will guide me, Allah will find a way out for me.
Even though his eyes were telling him otherwise and his ears were telling him otherwise,
his eyes tell him it's impossible.
The sea and the army, his ears are telling him, it's impossible.
Because of all of the whispering of Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل) but his heart is telling him no!
His heart is telling him believe in Allah.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ split the sea for Musa(موسى) and destroyed Firaun(فرعون).
Therefore Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will find a way out for you and to apply this on an individual basis
we talked about it on the society level on an individual basis,
if you have Taqwa(تقوى) in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will provide a way out for you,
in case you get into trouble, or in case you are poor, on in case you are in need,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will find a way out for you.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will help you, have that Yaqeen(يقين) in Allah
وَمَن يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَل لَّهُ مَخْرَجًا ۝ وَيَرْزُقْهُ مِنْ حَيْثُ لَا يَحْتَسِبُ
Rizq(رزق) will come to you.
Younus عليه السّلام was stuck in the stomach of the whale, under three levels of darkness
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ delivered him to safety, because of his Taqwa(تقوى).
Abdullah Bin Zaid Al-Ansari(عبدالله بن زيد ألأنصاري) travelled to Madina
to deliver the news to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was delivering Khutba(خطبه) on the Mimber(ممبر), on the pulpit
and he saw Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) coming in.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was, by the way,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would be extremely concerned with,
what is happening on the front lines
and he would sometimes be so excited to know the news.
He would go outside of Madina in order to meet the messengers
and he cannot sleep, he would spend his sleepless nights thinking about
what's happening with the Muslims on the front line and it would be making Dua(دُعَا) for them.
So, as soon as this Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) coming in and he is on the Mimber(ممبر)
he said: What's the news?
He cut the Khutba(خطبه) and he said: "What's the news?"
Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) was very wise, he did not answer he said;
أَتَاكَ الّْخَبَرْ يا أمير الّمومنين
News is on its way to you Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين),
until he crossed the lines and he came to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين)
and he whispered the news into his ears.
He did not want to give the news publicly
until the Khalifah(خليفه) delivers it himself because it's not good news.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه  said;
أَللَّهُمَّ كُلَّ مُسْلِمٍ فِيْ حِلٍّ مِنِّيْ أَنَا فِئَةْ كُلِّ مُسْلِمٍ
مَنْ لَّقِيَ الّعَدُوْ فَفُظِعَ بِشَيْءٍ مِّنْ أَمْرِهِ فَأَناَ لَه’ فِئَةَ
يَرْحَمُ اللهُ أَبَا عُبَيْد، لَوْ كَانَ إِنْحَازَإِلَيَّ لَكُنْتُ لَه’ فِئَة
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I am the Fea(فِئَةَ) of every Muslim.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says in Qur'an;
إِلَّا مُتَحَرِّفًا لِّقِتَالٍ أَوْ مُتَحَيِّزًا إِلَىٰ فِئَةٍۢ
You are not allowed to retreat from the battle.
وَمَن يُوَلِّهِمْ يَوْمَئِذٍۢ دُبُرَهُۥٓ إِلَّا مُتَحَرِّفًا لِّقِتَالٍ أَوْ مُتَحَيِّزًا إِلَىٰ فِئَةٍۢ فَقَدْ بَآءَ بِغَضَبٍۢ مِّنَ ٱللَّهِ
And we know that retreating from the battle is one of the seven major sins.
You are not allowed to retreat from the battle except in two situations.
Number one, you are making a tactical retreat in order to attack again
or Number two, you are retreating to join with another Muslim force or group.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I am that force for every Muslim.
May Allah have mercy on Abu Obaid(أبوعبيد)! Why didn't he come back to me?
Why did he have to carry on fighting?
Why didn't he come back to me and I would be the force in which he could fall back on,
and I would give him reinforcements to go back and fight.
See, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was thinking about it from the approach of the leader,
Abu Obaid(أبوعبيد) might have been thinking about it from another approach.
There are two options dying as a shaheed or victory.
إِمَّاالّقَتْلَ وَإِمَّا الشَّهَادَةْ
And these are called.
"إِهْدَالّحُسْنَيَيْنَ"
The two goods, the two virtues, one is dying as a shaheed(شهيد)
and the other one is being victorious.
From a strictly reward point of view
it is more rewarding to die as the shaheed(شهيد) than it is to win.
Therefore on an individual basis the Sahabah(صحابه) would want to die
because it carries more Ajr(أجْر).
However, the leader Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) since he is the Khalifah(خليفه)
he is more concerned with having Islam spread, being victorious, winning.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was very careful
and he did not want the Muslims to fall into destruction and perish.
And that was the concern of the Khulafaa(خلفاء).
Umar Bin Abdel Aziz رضي الله عنه, the first thing he did as soon as it became Khalifah(خليفه).
He gave orders to have the army that is laying siege to Constantinople to come back.
Why? Because that army was suffering the cold weather and hunger and they were dying.
The only reason why the previous Khalifah(خليفه) had them there, is out of stubbornness.
He wanted Constantinople to fall.
And even though he was receiving news that the Muslims were dying
because of hunger, disease and cold weather.
He had the army carry on laying that siege.
Umar Bin Abdel Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) immediately, called the Muslims back.
Even though everyone who was dying, was dying as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Ash-Shaibani(ألمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني) is now the leader again.
He has assume leadership in many different battles
he was also the leader in the time of Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So, now he became the leader he asked for reinforcements.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sent him some reinforcements.
Same thing happens because Iraq is the land of rivers.
He was on the river and the enemy was across him.
And they said: Do you want to cross over to us or shall we cross over to you.
He said: "No you cross over to us".
We are not crossing over to you, you come to us.
They  cross over, Al-Musanna(ألمثنى) gives his instructions to the Muslims,
you make Takbeer(تكبير),
first Takbeer(تكبير), second Takbeer(تكبير), third Takbeer(تكبير), fourth Takbeer(تكبير) and then you charge.
But the Persian army did not give them that chance.
they attacked immediately after the first Takbeer(تكبير).
Al-Musanna(مثنى) has told his army previously, this was Ramadan(رمضان).
He said: You are fasting and fasting weakens your body.
My advice is that you break your fast.
They followed his advice, and they broke their fast.
He told them, that food will strengthen you.
So, they had their meal middle of the day, even though this was Ramadan(رمضان).
So, they are allowed to break their fast if, it is Harb(حرب), if it is war
that is established in the Shariah(شريعة), because at that particular moment,
the fighting is more virtuous than the fasting.
So, it takes precedence over fasting,
and even if somebody wants to combine between fighting and fasting,
it is better that they don't, because fasting weakens you.
And you need to have all of the stamina and strength that you can.
So, he had them break their fasting.
Also in this particular Battle of Boweb(ألبُوَيب).
After the Muslims won, they won this battle.
Al-Muthanna(مثنى) sent food to the women's camp.
These are the families that accompany their husbands.
So, they were not close to the battle ground there were far away to keep them safe,
Al-Musanna(مثنى) he sent a Christian man to take that food to the woman.
He's an Arab Christian and he had a group of men with him and they're taking the food
to the women and children when the women saw them coming,
they didn't know who they were.
So, they all armed themselves with poles
and sticks and went out to fight, when this man saw that,
he said: "This is how women should be"
and then he gave them the news of victory.
He said: I am here just to give you this food and not here to fight,
but this shows us that the woman in those days were strong
and they were stronger than the men today.
The Sahabiaat(صحابيات) and Tabiaat(تابيعات) would be willing to fight, if they had to,
not only if they had to but some of them volunteered in fighting like Nusaiba Bint Ka'abرضي الله عنها,
and some of the other Ansaar(أنْصَار),
Ansaariaat(أنصاريات) especially the woman of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) were strong,
don't you remember the what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
We used to have the upper hand over our women in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) in Makkah.
And we come here and we find women, who had the upper hand over their husbands.
So, the women of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) were strong, not only at their homes,
but also in the battlefield.
Nusaiba Bint Ka'ab(نُصيبه بنت كعب) was involved in fighting
and she said: I had 12 injuries in my body on the day of Yarmook(يرموك),
Khalid Bin Waleed رضي الله عنه sent me a physician to take care of me
because he was a man who took great care of us.
And then she said, she had 12 injuries in her body.
And the way they would heal those injuries in those days is,
what would they do?
Would they bring any anti bacteria, medicine and antibiotics.
What they would do, is they would pour over the injury, boiling oil,
they would pour over the injury, boiling oil.
What that does is, it kills the germs.
So, it prevents infections and it also stops the bleeding
and it burns the surface of the injury and that helps the healing.
So, it seals it.
It burnt, it sealed, no infections can get in.
She said, that the healing process was more painful than the injuries themselves.
So, this tells you that these were very strong women,
these were very strong women, for her to have patience to endure all of that pain - voluntarily.
I mean, she chose to go into it and because it's not fardh(فرض) on them.
She chose to, it tells you something about their love of Allah
because remember, in those days there was no anesthesia.
The next battle or series of raids really, commanded by Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Ash-Shaibani(ألمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني)
were against economical targets of the enemy.
He attacked their markets,
they had these markets, where all of the businessmen would come.
It's like a fairground or tradeshow, you'd name it, whatever you want.
So, they would bring all of their items merchandise to this market.
And they would have more than one market, Al-Muthanna(ألمثنى) targeted these markets
and he told his men to take nothing but gold and silver,
you leave the food behind you leave the clothes behind, you just go after the gold and silver.
And you only take other items, you take as much as your camel can carry, don't take more.
But you should devote the effort to targeting the gold and silver.
The reasoning behind that is Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Ash-Shaibani(ألمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني)
wants to finance his campaigns against the enemy from his enemies own pocket.
Number two, the Muslims were in need.
And Number three, it is to weaken the enemy.
So, it was an economical war against the Persian Empire.
So, they raided these markets and they did it with lightening speed
headed by Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Ash-Shaibani(ألمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني).
They used the best horses that they had, the Arabian horses very fast
and they're on their way back and it all happened within one day.
And they covered the distance of more than 60 miles, which is quite significant.
Talking about their form of transportation in those days.
You travelled, you attacked, you come back.
On their way back, they heard some noise.
So, one of the soldiers said: This must be an army attacking us.
Al-Musanna Bin Harisa Ash-Shaibani(ألمثنى بن حارثه ألشيباني), he said;
تَنَاجَوْا بِالْبِرِّ وَالتَّقْوَى وَلَا تَنَاجَوْ بِالْإ ثْمِ وَالْعُدْوَانَ
Don't speak evil but speak good.
أُنْظُرُوْا فِي الّأُمُوْرِ وَقَدِّرُوْهَاأحسبوها ثُمَّ تَكَلَّمُوْا
Think about you say before you say it.
Think about it, assess the situation make the right judgment and then speak,
don't speak first.
إِنَّه’ لَمْ يَبْلُغَ ألْتَدَّبِرْمَدِيْنَتَهُمْ بَعْدْ
وَلَوْبَلَغَهُمْ لَحَالَ الرُّعْبَ بَيْنَهُمْ وَبَيْنَ طَلَبِكُمْ
Their army didn't even received the warning yet.
Not only is the army not following us, they didn't even know about what happened
our attack was so swift and fast the news didn't even reached the army
and then he said: And if it did, fear will prevent them from following you
because these raids throw fear in the hearts of the enemy
and this fear can last for an entire day, these swift ambushes,
they cast fear in the hearts of the enemy as Musanna Bin Harisa(مثنى بن حارثه) said;
It will make them terrified, it would put them in a state of shock for 24 hours,
don't worry they're not going to come.
إِنَّ لِلْغَارَاتِ رَوْعَاتْ تَنْتَشِرُ عَلَيْهَا يَوْمًا إِلَى الَّيْلَ
وَلَوْ أَدْرَكُوْكُمْ لَقَا تَلْنَهُمْ لِاثْنَتَيْنَ، إِلْتَمَاسَ الْأَجْرَ وَرَجَاءًالنَّصَرْ
And if they do come, so What?
We'll fight them for two reasons to get the Ajr(أجْر) the from Allah and to get victory.
إِنَّ خليفة رسول الله أَبَا بَكْر أَوْصَانَا أَنْ نُقَلِّلَ ألْعَرْجِّةْ
وَنُسْرِعَ ألْكَرَّةَّ فِيْ الّغَارَاتَ وَنُسْرِعَ فِيْ غَيْرِ ذَلِكَ
I'm doing this because the Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Ullah, Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه told me
to be very swift and fast in my raids.
This was the advice of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) that he gave to Musanna(مثنى) to be very fast.
It's pretty much similar to what is called today the guerrilla warfare method.
Which is based on small groups attacking swiftly and retreating after ambushing the enemy.
What was the response of the people of Faris.
What happened to them was because of what Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ created among them.
The disunity that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ created among them.
So, the people are Faris(فارس), Persia came to Rustum(رستم) and Feroze(فيروز) and they said;
أَيْنَ يَذْهَبْ بِكُمُا الْإِخْتِلَافَ حَتَّى وَهَنْتُمَا أَهْلِ فَارِس
This disunity of yours has weakened the people of Persia.
وَأَطْمَاتُمَا فِيْهِمْ عَدُوَّهُمْ
And you made the enemy greedy in our land.
وَالله مَا جَرَّ هَذَا أَلّوَهَنْ عَلَيْنَا غَيْرَكُمْ يَا مَعْشَرَالْقُوَّادَ
This defeat that we are suffering now is because of you our leaders.
لَقَدْ فَرَّقْتُّمْ بَيْنَ أَهَل لْفَارِس وَثَبَّطّتُمُوْهُمْ عَنْ عَدُوِّهِمْ
مَا بَعْدَ بَغْدَادْ وَسَابَاطْ وَتَكْرِيْتَ إِلَّا الْمَدَائِنْ
What is left after Baghdad(بغداد), Sabaat(سبات) and Tikrit(تكريت) except Al-Madaen(ألمدائن)?
So, they mentioned the names of some of the major towns that fell.
They said: Tikrit(تكريت), Baghdad(بغداد) and Sabaat(سبات) have fell under the Muslims.
All what is left is our capital Al-Madaen(ألمدائن).
So, they said;
وَالله لَتَجْتَمِعَانْ أَوْلَنَبْدِأَنَّ بِكُمَا قَبْلَ أَنْ يَشْمَتَ بِنَا شَامِتْ
You either unify our ranks or we're going to kill you first.
وَالله لَوْ لَا أَنَّ فِيْ قَتْلِكُمْ هَلَاكُنَا لَعَجَّلْنَا لَكُمُ الْقَتْلَ السَّاعَة
If it wasn't that killing, you will weaken us further, we would have killed you first.
وَلَئِنْ لَّمْ تَنْتَهُوْا لَنُهْلِكَنَّكُمْ ثُمَّ نَهْلَكْ  وَقَدْ أَشْتَفَيْنَا مِنْكُمْ
And if you don't unify now, we will kill you
even if we're going to end up losing.
So, that when we lose, we would at least have taken revenge from you.
Because this is happening because of you.
These were very serious threats from the people of Persia.
They're waken up to the threat knocking on their doors.
The Muslims were now way into Iraq.
So, what they did is,
This was a kingdom, it was ruled by Royal Family,
and you had to have royal blood to be the king.
However, one of their earlier kings, what he did was,
he gathered all of his brothers and their sons and he executed them all.
The reason why he did that is he doesn't want anyone to compete with him in the future.
So, He wanted the royal blood to dry out.
So, that he ensures that he will carry on.
What he really did was he shot himself in the foot, he died,
and there was nobody to take over after him.
So, the kingdom was transferred to a woman from the royal family,
and then she was killed.
So, another woman took over, and she was incapable of leading the Empire,
and that is when Rustam(رستم) and Feroze(فيروز) who are not from the royal family
but they are military generals.
They started taking affairs in their own hands.
They didn't claim to be kings, but they were the actual runners of the affairs of Persia.
They were the administrators but since there was no figurehead to lead them.
These two men Feroze(فيروز) and Rustam(رستم) started clashing.
So, what they did,
they gathered all of the women from the royal family of Sassan(ساسان)
and they had them tortured, they were torturing the women from the royal family,
and telling them, trying to extract from them any information.
If there is a surviving male member in the family,
and they were torturing them to get that information.
One of them did in fact claim that there is one man from the royal family,
who is in this faraway area.
And the reason, why he is there is, because his mother feared for his death.
So, she smuggled him away before the king killed all of the male members of the family,
they investigated that story and found it to be true.
So, they called in this young man.
He was 21 years old, his name is Yastajard(يزدجرد)
and they appointed him as Emperor over them.
He was 21 years old, he is Yastajard Al thalith (يزدجردالثالث) the third,
and he now succeeded in unifying the people of the Persian Empire
so now things were different.
Now, the Muslims will be facing a unified foe.
They would be facing the entire Sassaani Empire.
They started mobilizing their forces from the four corners of the Empire,
and news was reaching to Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
that the Persian Empire is ready to face us with the largest army, they have assembled so far.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) decided to go out himself and meet the Persian army,
all of the Sahabah(صحابه) agreed to that suggestion
except one Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف).
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) said: If you are killed,
then the Muslims will have no one to go back to,
but why don't you send someone in your place and you stay behind in Madina.
So, if the Muslims lose, then you would be able to lead another campaign against them
and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) insisted on his opinion,
and he succeeded in convincing, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) to stay behind.
But now, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: So, who can I appoint
for this major battle?
Who is the person who could take care of this major affair?
And he was thinking about it for days, who should I appoint?
And then one of the Sahabah(صحابه) came to him and said: I found it, I found it,
I found the person.
He said: Who is it?
He said: It's the lion in his den.
He said, Who is it?
The man is getting Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) excited.
He said: It's a lion in his den!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Who is it?
Who is that lion?
He said: Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد إبن أبي وقاص).
One of the 10 who are given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
A relative of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You have found him.
And he appointed him to lead the army
that would end up fighting one of The most famous battles in our Muslim history.
One of The most important battles ever in the time of Al-Khulafaa(ألْخلفاء).
In fact, it only has one competitor, and that is Ghazwa Al-Yarmook(غزوة اليرموك).
That's the only battle to compete with the importance of this battle.
And what's the name of this battle…?
Al-Qaadsiyaa(ألقادسیة),
Maarikat-Qadisiyyah(معركة القادسية)
This issue was so important Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) overruled
a order that was or a law that was legislated by Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه
and that is that none of the men, who joined in the armies of Ridda(ردة),
against the Muslims should participate in Jihad(جهاد).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) refused to accept
the former murtaddeen(مرتدين) into the Muslim army.
Many of these murtaddeen(مرتدين) or all of them, the ones that at least survived
all of them, they came back to Islam.
But Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) didn't want them, to join the Muslim army.
You stay out.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was so short of men,
he had to recruit the former Murtaddeen(مرتدين).
And now he opened up the gates of recruitment, anyone is welcomed
we need any help that we can get.
So, many of the former Murtaddeen(مرتدين), now they are Muslim they joined in.
Not only that, but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he did not get enough,
when he opened up the doors of recruitment or voluntary,
he didn't received enough soldiers.
He started mandatory military service.
So, the first one to start mandatory military service was Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
He sent out letters to the Muslim states saying that any man, who has weapons
and is able to fight must join in the armies.
Why? Because now, we have the major battle of Qaadsiya(قادسية)
and we also have the Roman front which was still going on.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) needed anyone that could offer help
to step forward and come and join the Armies.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه asked Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد بن أبي وقاص)
to send a delegation to meet with the Persian Emperor.
So, they sent a delegation of 14 men many of them Sahabah(صحابه)
like Mugheerah Bin Shoba(مغيرة بن شعبه), Noman Bin Makran(نعمان بن مقرن) and others,
they went to Yastajard(يزدجرد) and they delivered to him the message from the Khalifah(خليفه).
We are inviting you to Islam, we were people who were misguided
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ guided us through Muhammad ﷺ,
and now we are delivering to you the same invitation that He gave to us.
An-Noman Ibn Makran(نعمان بن مقرن) closed his speech by saying We give you three options.
Number one: You  become Muslim if you do, we would leave you and your land alone.
Number two: If you refuse to become Muslim then we give you the option of paying Jizya(جزية).
If you refused to pay us Jizya(جزية).
Than it is the sword.
Yastajard(يزدجرد) wasn't happy to hear somebody speaking to him like that,
how do you speak to the Emperor in such a way.?
You're not following the protocols.
He said: You were men who were humbled, and never dreamt of attacking our empire.
So, what has happened to you,
if the reason why you are here in our land is beacuse you're hungry, we will feed you.
We will give you back money to go back to your desert.
Noman Bin Makran(نعمان بن مقرن) said;
Number one: You become Muslim if you don't, you pay us Jizya(جزية).
If you don't, then we will fight you.
Yastajard(يزدجرد) said: If it wasn't because messengers are not killed,
I would have killed you all.
Leave!....
So, they left.
That was the first delegation that was sent.
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص) sent another delegation to the leader of the army which is Rustum(رُستم).
Rustum(رُستم) is now going to lead the battle in Al-Qadsiya(ألقادسية).
Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص) sent Rab'ee Ibn Amir رضي الله عنه to meet with him.
And that is when an interesting conversation took place.
We'll talk about that In Sha Allah ho Ta'Allah(إن شاء الله تعالى) tomorrow night.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
You might have time for a question or two?
You mentioned in one of your previous sessions if a Muslim leaves Islam than he should be executed.
Is there any Qur'an Ayah(آية) or it's from Sunnah(سنة)?
It's from Sunnah.
"مَنْ بَدَّلَ دِيْنَه’ فَاقْتُلُوْهْ"
Whoever changes his religion, then execute him.
However, any punishment can only be carried out by the Sultan(سلطان), by the leader.
Law is not taken into individuals hands.
It has to be done through the Muslim government.
You said that Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد إبن أبي وقاص) made Dua(دُعَا) against the man that slandered him,
however we as Muslims should we not make Dua(دُعَا) for them rather than against them?
Which evil against them? Well,
we are allowed to make Dua(دُعَا) against the person if the person oppresses us,
but don’t make Dua(دُعَا) against somebody who, who just hurt you in a very insignificant way.
Don't make Dua(دُعَا) is somebody who is otherwise righteous and good,
just because they made a mistake once.
You make the Dua(دُعَا) against Zalama(ظلماء)
the people to whom oppression is part of their life, the tyrants
you make Dua(دُعَا) against these.
That’s what Musa عليه السّلام did against Firaun(فرعون).
رَبَّنَا اطْمِسْ عَلَىٰ أَمْوَالِهِمْ وَاشْدُدْ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ فَلَا يُؤْمِنُوا حَتَّىٰ يَرَوُا الْعَذَابَ الْأَلِيمَ۝
O Allah seal their hearts and destroy their wealth, until they see the punishment from You.
Meaning don't give them a chance to make Toba(توبة).
And Noah عليه السّلام said;
لَا تَذَرْ عَلَى الْأَرْضِ مِنَ الْكَافِرِينَ دَيَّارًا۝
إِنَّكَ إِنْ تَذَرْهُمْ يُضِلُّوا عِبَادَكَ وَلَا يَلِدُوا إِلَّا فَاجِرًا كَفَّارًا۝
O Allah don't leave any disbelieving soul alive on the face of the earth,
he made Dua(دُعَا) against all of the Kafara(كفارا).
Rasool Allah ﷺ made Dua(دُعَا) against Raqal(رقل) and Aquaan(أقعان) and Urana(عرنة),
he made Dua(دُعَا) against some of the Arab tribes who betrayed him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه made Dua(دعا) against the People of the Book who are fighting him.
So Dua(دُعَا) against someone is allowed.
But this should not be interpreted to mean that somebody walked next to you
and just hit you and didn't say excuse me.
So, you start, you raise your hands and you make Dua(دُعَا) him.
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE